Guide to the Division of Social Work, Marion Hathway Files, University of Pittsburgh, 1930-1938 UA.90.18.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Division of Social Work, Marion Hathway Files, University of Pittsburgh
1930-1938
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hathway, Marion
UA.90.18.1
7.2 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
This collection documents the development of the University of Pittsburgh School of Social Work from 1930 to 1938.
Related Material
The University Archives Personal Files contains an information folder on Marion Hathway which contains news clipping, photographs and short manuscripts.
The Marion Hathway Papers are located at the Social Welfare History Archives, University of Minnesota Libraries (https://www.lib.umn.edu/swha).
Arrangement
These files are largely in the original order and with original file headings.
Custodial History
This collection was discovered in March of 2012 in a passageway on the 21st floor of the Cathedral of Learning at the University of Pittsburgh. The passageway was behind a sealed panel of a room that served as the Office of the Dean of the School of Social Work from its earliest days until 1992. Shortly thereafter, Dr. Edward Sites, Professor Emeritus of the School of Social Work, began the task of cleaning and organizing the collection. He deposited this collection in the University Archives in March of 2014 and provided much of the historical and biographical context of the description herein.
Acquisition Information
Deposited in the University Archives by Edward W. Sites, Professor Emeritus, on behalf of the School of Social Work Dean's Office, on March 6, 2014.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection documents in detail the development of the School of Social Work from its predecessor: the Division of Social Work in the Department of Sociology. Much of this details the process that led to the School's development and accreditation. There is also significant information on the research and training in social work in Pittsburgh during the 1920's through the 1940's.
History
The School of Social Work began very modestly as a set of courses in sociology and a social work training program administered in the School of Economics (later the Business School). It was eliminated from that school in 1921 and re-established in 1926 as part of the Department of Applied Social Sciences. The School of Social Work grew out of the Department of Sociology's graduate level program in training social workers. It was called the Division of Social Work. Marion Hathaway was hired as an assistant professor of sociology in 1933 but taught classes in this graduate, professional training course in Social Work.
Chronology:
1926 – Manuel C. Elmer becomes head of the Pitt Department of Sociology
1931 – Division of Social Work first organized as a separate unit. The degree that students earned was Master of Arts in Social Work.
May, 1932 – Correspondence begins with the American Association of Schools of Professional Social Work (AASPSW). The secretary of the Association was Mary Burnett of the Department of Sociology at Carnegie Institute of Technology.
January 1933 – The Division of Social Work makes formal application for membership in the AASPSW. The president is Dr. M. J. Karpf.
February 1933 – AASPSW President Phelps writes raising questions about whether the University of Pittsburgh meets the requirements for membership. He raised 6 fundamental questions.
July 1933 – Dr. Marion Hathway joins the faculty of the Department of Sociology at Pitt as an assistant professor
July 19, 1933 – Pitt submits a revised application for membership to the AASPSW.
December 6 - 10, 1933 – Dr. Karpf makes a site visit to Pitt. He meets with Drs. Elmer and Hathway among others.
December 1933 – Dr. Karpf writes to the Family Society of Allegheny County regarding field work problems and the School responds to issues raised by Dr. Karpf
May 1934 – Pitt submits further documentation in support of its application for membership in the AASPSW. in June Marion Hathway responds further to questions raised by the AASPSW
July 1934 – Marion Hathway is appointed Assistant Director of the Division of Social Work and the AASPSW Committee reviewing Pitt's application for membership decides to grant the School's admission to the Association.
October 17, 1934 – Marion Hathway further responds and outlines Pitt's progress in meeting recommendations of the AASPSW
January, 1935 – Pitt's reports to the AASPSW. the enrollment is 252 students (232 women and 29 men).
Previous Citation
Division of Social Work, Marion Hathway Files, University of Pittsburgh, 1930-1938, UA.90.18.1, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Correspondence; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social work education -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh; Clippings (Information artifacts); Hathway, Marion; American Association of Social Workers; American Association of Schools of Social Work; Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania; University of Pittsburgh. Graduate School of Social Work -- Faculty; University of Pittsburgh -- Curricula; University of Pittsburgh. Graduate School of Social Work -- History
- Abbot, Edith (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Correspondence between Marion Hathway, Assistant Director Division of Social Work, University of Pittsburgh and Miss Edith Abbott, Dean of the Graduate School of Social Service Administration, University of Chicago – April, 1933 - January, 1937
  Contents:
  Letters of reference; Negotiations for the publication in book form of Marion Hathway's doctoral dissertation, "The Migratory Worker" by the University of Chicago Press; Recruitment for faculty and community agency vacancies in Pittsburgh; Discussion of arrangements for Dean Abbott to speak in Pittsburgh; Discussion of public welfare reform in Pennsylvania; Discussion of training of "emergency relief workers" by schools of social work; Mention of Pitt social work program extensions in Erie and New Castle in 1934
- Administration, July, 1933 – March, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes Hathway's 1933 letter of acceptance of appointment as Assistant Professor of Sociology in the College; Correspondence urging faculty to support the fund raising effort on behalf of the "Complete-the-Cathedral Campaign."; Correspondence on behalf of Miss Pauline Redmond, the first Urban League Fellow "to take a degree in social work."; Correspondence regarding subsequent appointments of Miss Hathway to the faculty; A letter to Chancellor John G. Bowman in October, 1937 regarding the forthcoming accreditation site visit by Mr. W. I. Newstetter of Case Western Reserve University on behalf of the American Association of Schools of Social Work of which Miss Hathway was the secretary and a member of the Association's Executive Committee; Confidential memoranda detailing the agenda of faculty meetings of "the College"
- Advertising (Box 1, Folder 3)
- A - General Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Responses to inquiries regarding the Division of Social Work or study at Pitt; Invitations to speak and invitations to speakers; Brief exchange with Grace Abbott; Information on requirements for admission to study social work in about 10 other universities; Information on several national conferences; Responses to requests for referrals to fill social work positions; Miscellaneous correspondence on a variety of other subjects.
- American Association of Schools of Social Work, Application for Admission, May 1932-October 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Advisory Committee, Division of Social Work, 1931-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  Correspondence from leading social agency executives responding to an invitation to serve on the Division of Social Work's Advisory Board; Drafts of lists of prospective Board membership; Notes of discussion topics for meeting addenda; Draft list of membership of Committee on Policy; Reports of October, 1933 and March, 1934 meetings of the Advisory Committee; List of membership of Case Work Committee; Lists of Advisory Committee members; Invitations to and responses from persons invited to serve on Division of Social Work's Advisory Committee; November 1936 Summary of Agency Conference on Field Work Minor.
- Advisory Committee on Group Work, December 1931-March 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  List of Advisory Committee on Group Work membership; Invitations to and responses from agency personnel in the community inviting them to serve on the Advisory Committee.
- Advisory Committee on Medical Social Work, October 1931-March 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  List of Advisory Committee on Medical Social Work members; Program from the Dedication of Falk Clinic, September 28, 1931; Handwritten notes from a speech apparently given in connection with the dedication of Falk Clinic; Invitations to and responses from agency personnel in the community inviting them to serve on the Medical Social Work Advisory Committee.
- Advisory Committee on Policy (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Allegheny County Board of Assistance, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  List of Allegheny County Board of Assistance offices and personnel; Copy of study completed by Belle B. Glosser titled "Applications for Old Age Assistance from Residents of Public Institutions in Allegheny County"
- Allegheny County Emergency Relief Board, 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Minutes and notes of meetings among state, county and university representatives regarding training of emergency relief workers in Allegheny County; Lists of students placed for training in various ACERB offices; Related correspondence; Marion Hathway's syllabus for course "The State and Social Welfare"
- ACERB – Correspondence, February 1934–February 1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Correspondence among such persons as Marion Hathway, Nell Scott, Bess Long, George Mills, Esther Goodyear and Ruth Camblon
- American Association of Schools of Social Work Course Outlines, 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  American Association of Schools of Social Work Minimum Curriculum adopted at the December 1932 Meeting of the AASSW; American Association of Schools of Social Work News Letter, January 1, 1936. Sophonisba P. Breckinridge appears to have been the editor.
  Syllabi for: Psychiatry in Social Work, Social Work and the Law, Basic Case Work, Public Welfare Administration, Social Statistics, Medical Courses for Social Workers, Labor Problems, Community Organization, Child Welfare, Field Work, Basic Course in Psychiatry, Field Instruction in Group Work.
- American Association of Schools of Social Work, Correspondence, January 1935-April 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  General correspondence with such persons as Mildred Mudgett, Sophonisba Breckinridge and Marion Hathway; Program from Annual Meeting of the American Association of Schools of Social Work at the YWCA in New Orleans January 27-29, 1938. This was the meeting at which Pitt's application for membership in the Association (the term for accreditation) was acted upon. Sophonisba Breckenridge was the Association's president and Marion Hathway was its secretary.
- American Association of Social Workers, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  Memorandum from Karl de Schweinitz; Multiple copies of a reprint promoting the American Association of Social Workers; Marion Hathway's correspondence and telegrams regarding AASW business nationally and in Pennsylvania; Correspondence regarding civil service coverage of social workers in Pennsylvania; Proposed requirements for admission of group workers to membership in the American Association of Social Workers; Organizational matters of the American Association of Social Workers; Extensive correspondence on requirements for membership in the American Association of Social Workers; Correspondence regarding standards for acceptance under AASW's membership requirements of courses in schools of social work.
- American Association of Social Workers, Pennsylvania Division, January 1934-February 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- American Association of Social Workers, Pittsburgh Chapter, January 1934-February 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Minutes of the Pittsburgh Chapter of the Pennsylvania Division of the American Association of Social workers; Membership lists of the Pittsburgh Chapter, PA Div., AASW; Reports of the Committee on Public and Private Relief; Fiscal data on City of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County.
- American Association of University Professors, October 1935-May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- American Association of University Women, September 1934-July 1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  AAUW, Pittsburgh Branch membership list 1934 – 1935; Correspondence regarding a research study.
- American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees, June 1936-January 1937 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Minutes and correspondence regarding the establishment of a "merit system" or civil service system in Pennsylvania; Data on number of employees in various departments of PA state government; Number of employees in all of PA government 1919–1933.
- American Public Welfare Association, January 1936-December 1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Correspondence including a January 1936 request by Dr. Hathway for 25 copies of the Social Security Act and the response from the APWA that their supply had been exhausted; Conference programs; APWA agency membership list.
- American University, January 1937-June1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Extensive correspondence regarding a program at American University on Social Security; Information on employment placement of participants in the program.
- Annual Report Form Letters, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Applications for Position in Division, July 1934–December 1936 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- B - General Correspondence, November 1934–June 1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Correspondence regarding appearance of former Governor of Minnesota, A. O. Eberhart; Correspondence regarding students placed in Federal Emergency Relief Administration settings; Correspondence with Washington University Clinics and Allied Hospital Director Edith M. Baker regarding research at Allegheny General Hospital in Pittsburgh; Letter from PA DPW regarding Cambria County's decision not to employ trained social workers based upon a study that purported to show that "children had been unwisely placed and the report is an exposé of bad results from foster home care."; Correspondence with the president of West Virginia University regarding social work extension courses in Wheeling, West Virginia; Correspondence with the president of West Virginia University regarding candidates for faculty positions as West Virginia University attempted to create a social work program.
- Bernstein, Dr. Ludwig B., May 1934–August 1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Correspondence regarding service as vice chair of the Pittsburgh Chapter of the American Association of Social Workers, Bernstein's role as instructor in social work and his move to California.
- Bishop, Julia Ann (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Case Supervisor, Rural Extension Unit, Child Welfare Services, Social Security Act.
- Budget (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Correspondence with Wilbur I. Newstetter regarding Division of Social Work budget; Information regarding compensation for instructors in the Division of Social Work; A list of the 1937-1938 Division of Social Work faculty and their salaries.
- Buhl Lectures and Institutes, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  Correspondence with speakers regarding program and honoraria; Programs with speakers and topics; Speakers include Norman Thomas, Frances Perkins, James Weldon Johnson, Charlotte Towle, Bertha Reynolds and Ruth Benedict.
- Burnett, Mrs. Mary C., 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Mary C. Burnett was the Director of Training for the Pennsylvania State Emergency Relief Board. This file contains correspondence regarding the establishment of a "merit system" in PA, enrollment of students in the social work program at Pitt and the 1937-1938 Annual Report (of the inaugural year) on enrollment in the Department of Social Work at Carnegie Institute of Technology.
- C - General Correspondence, June 1933-May 1938 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Letters of reference; Correspondence regarding conference planning and speaking engagements; Correspondence regarding a meeting in Pittsburgh of the American Birth Control League, Inc.; Several child welfare items including a June 24, 1937 letter from Mary Irene Atkinson, Director, Child Welfare Division, Children's Bureau, US Department of Labor, writes to Pitt to say "…we have approved plans which included provision for educational leaves. In most instances leaves have been given only to persons who had had at least one quarter or (sic) professional training previously and who had also had some experience as a paid worker on a social work staff. The experience of the past year and a half leads us to the conclusion that this as been a sound procedure."
- Camblon, Mrs. Ruth B., September 1934-February 1937 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  1. Correspondence regarding the successful recruitment of Ruth Camblon from the Washington, DC Child Guidance Clinic as "field work supervisor."; Correspondence from Mrs. Camblon to Dr. Hathway.
- Catalogue Material (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Drafts of the 1938-1939 Division of Social Work "catalog" including personnel, course descriptions, tuition, etc.
- Catholic Charities, September 1931-April 1938 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  Extensive correspondence largely between the new executive director of Catholic Charities of Pittsburgh (Miss M. Luella Sauer) and Marion Hathway, Manuel Elmer and Harold A. Phelps regarding field work placements, physical examinations of prospective students, students enrolled at Pitt from Catholic Charities, and a problem meeting American Association of Social Workers standards for approving Catholic Charities as a field site.
  January 7, 1935 correspondence congratulates the University of Pittsburgh on its Division of Social Work being approved for full membership in the American Association of Schools of Social Work. This would have been tantamount to receiving accreditation.
  The Basis of a Program of Catholic Family Social Work by Mary Luella Sauer Notes of interview of M. Luella Sauer by Ruth B. Camblon and correspondence regarding students
- Child Guidance Center, Student Field Work Placement, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Children's Aid Society, 1932-1938 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Includes lists of students placed at the Children's Aid Society from the first semester 1934-1935 to the second semester, 1937-1938
- Children's Service Bureau, April 1932-June 1938 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Largely correspondence between Marin Hathway and Susan M. Boyd, Executive Secretary (and Case Work Supervisor) of the Children's Service Bureau; Correspondence concerns student "field work placements,"; "Confidential" correspondence regarding the implementation of the "Aid to Dependent Children" provisions of the new Social Security Act
- Child Welfare Institutes, 1934, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Brochure from institute held December 4 and 5, 1934 in collaboration with the Federation of Social Agencies entitled "Child Behavior and Foster Care"; Announcement of Child Welfare Institute on May1, 1936 entitled Programs for Child Caring Institutions"; Announcement of Child Welfare Conference on June 23, 1936 entitled "The Child, His food and Good Nutrition"
- Child Welfare Material, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  Case face sheet; Topics to be covered in supervision visits to children; Information desired in foster home investigation; Memorandum to visitors; New case investigation; Information to provident clinic; Other related information and forms.
- Chorynak, John, August 1937-April 1938 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  Listing with descriptions of four courses Dr. Chorynak was scheduled to teach in the 1937-1938 academic year; Correspondence with and about Dr. Chorynak, a psychiatrist with the Juvenile Court of Allegheny County. One letter concerns Hathway's attempt to locate a study Chorynak cited in one of his classes that he said showed "the destructive affects of social case workers in certain instances."
- Citizens Committee on the Social Study, March 1937-February 1938 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  Correspondence regarding "The Citizens' Committee for the Social Study of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County." It appears that Gordon Hamilton may have had a part in the "study."
  Progress reports by the Division of Social Work on implementing the recommendations resulting from the "study." One of these recommendations was "That at the University of Pittsburgh, the Division of Social Work should become a Department of Social Work co-equal with the other departments; with a full-time director who might however participate if desired in the instruction in other departments in the same way as the teaching force of other departments now is utilized in the Division of Social Work."
- Civil Service (Box 2, Folder 46)
  Primarily announcements for civil service examinations in the general area of social work in 1936 and 1937, includes city, state and federal as well as other states such as Illinois and Ohio
- Class Rolls, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 47-50)
  Information on classes and students.
- Clippings (Box 2, Folder 51)
  About a dozen newspaper clippings from 1937 and 1938 including an announcement of the arrival of "Wilbert (sic.) I. Newstetter" as Dean in September, 1938; the announcement by the University or the creation of the "School of Social Work" as the University's "18th separate school;" and the announcement of the resignation of Dr. Marion Hathway, associate professor of social work "to accept the executive secretaryship of the Association of Schools of Social Work."
- Coleman Home for Boys, July 1937-December 1938 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  Report of the Committee Appointed by the Federation of Social Agencies on the Application of the Coleman Home for Membership in the Community Fund, Dr. Marion Hathway, Chair and Dr. Hathway.s correspondence and minutes.
- Committees, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  Materials regarding several advisory committees the Division of Social Work was establishing. File belonged to Harold A. Phelps originally.
  Notes regarding committee membership including: Case Work, child welfare, protective and correctional agencies, children's Institutions, Group Work, Medical Social Work and Public Health, Public Welfare, Organization, and Policy.
- Committee on Training, February 1937-June 1938 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  Materials relating to the Committee on Training of the Federation of Social Agencies; Dr. Herbert L. Spencer (President of the Pennsylvania College for Women, now Chatham University) chaired the committee and Isabel P. Kennedy (the Executive Secretary of the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County) was the secretary of the committee; Correspondence from M. C. Elmer.
- National Committee on Volunteers in Social Work, January 1936-March 1936 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Hospital Service Association of Pittsburgh (Box 2, Folder 56)
  Newsletter and brochure for early health care plan.
- Community Fund, June 1937-May 1938 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Excerpt from the By-Laws of the Community Fund; Material regarding the application of the Coleman Home for membership in the Community Fund; Financial statement of The Community Fund in February, 1938; Minutes of Community Fund Board of Directors meetings; Correspondence with Dr. Marion Hathway
- Correctional Case Workers Association, letter from J. Warren Matson, December 1937 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Counsel Service Society, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  List of members of the Advisory Committee to Counsel Service Society; "A Few of the Suggestions Given in Mr. Matson's Study of the Jail Population in Pittsburgh, … June to September, 1934."
- County Executives Round Table, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- County Welfare Bill, December 1933-June 1935 (Box 2, Folder 61)